{
  "reference_number": "12740",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "We would like to see the Bill target zero emissions by 2040. The zero emissions target needs to be supported by yearly targets for\n the next 10 years and then 5 yearly targets leading to zero in 2050."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2040. We need a more aggressive target."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "New Zealand is responsible for New Zealand's emissions. We need to become experts at reducing emissions - not leave others to do\n\n it for us. We support the ‘firewall’ principle that New Zealand’s targets must be achieved by actual reductions in our own domestic\n emissions and not through the purchase of overseas carbon credits or an over-reliance on forests as carbon sinks."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "It should only allow the target to be shortened."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The budgets need to be matched by observable action by all NZ government agencies (including Crown Owned Entities) and service\n providers."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "We're going to need to adapt to changed circumstances as climate keeps changing our situation. Changes should only be allowed\n when they improve emissions reductions."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Changes should only be allowed when they improve emissions reductions. We cannot keep putting off the hard tasks for later."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The commission’s role should include: • devising binding climate budgets • identifying the level of reduction for each form of\n\ngreenhouse gas (long-lived and short-lived) • monitoring adherence to the set ‘firewall’ • monitoring progress towards our targets •\nmonitoring cumulative emissions • advising on adaptation. The Climate Change Commission should provide advice to the New\n\nZealand government. To ensure transparency and accountability, I support the Government being required to table all reports from\nthe Climate Change Commission to Parliament."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Having clear measurable goals and milestones is critical to getting carbon emission reductions."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "As authors of a guidebook on carbon farming (\"The Carbon Forest, 2010\") we observe that a weak ETS has resulted in insignificant\ncarbon emission reductions and a great sense of uncertainty. This uncertainty has prevented businesses from investing in (a) carbon\nsequestration, and (b) carbon emission reductions. The Zero Carbon Bill (and all government behaviors) need to be coherent with\n\nour Paris Climate Agreement commitments in order to provide certainty for business decision makers."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "Policy settings should be in accordance with the goal of meeting or exceeding the Paris Agreement."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Adaption should be covered separately as it entails dramatically different goals."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "We strongly support the passing of a legally binding climate law and the immediate creation of a Zero Carbon Act. We believe in a net-\nzero carbon future for New Zealand. We need to make dramatic reductions in our emissions to keep climate change limited to 1.5\n\ndegrees and protect our native flora and fauna, our societies and our important infrastructures for ourselves and future generations.\nWe must act now to make a positive difference. The key things we support in a Zero Carbon Act are: • an ambitious Act that follows\n\nthe climate science by covering all gases across all sectors • a target of net-zero greenhouse gas emissions by 2040 • an Act that\ntargets the emissions from transport, industrial activity, agriculture and all other sources • an Act that includes emissions budgets\n\nthat should be at least as important as fiscal budgets, with plans set by the Government to achieve these budget • well publicised\nrobust interim milestones for government departments and NZ as a whole • an independent Climate Change Commission of experts\nto monitor emissions and give advice to the Government to keep New Zealand on track for its emissions reduction goals. We support\n\nZero Carbon Act legislation that establishes the goal of limiting warming to 1.5 degrees. We should not settle for 2 degrees warming.\nAny higher limit than 1.5 degrees would result in devastating impacts for Pacific Island states and significant extinctions. That is not\n\nacceptable. To give us the best possibility of achieving no more than 1.5 degrees warming by the end of the century, we must start\nmaking rapid cuts in all greenhouse gas emissions now. We support a net-zero target of 2040, with the majority of cuts occurring\n\nover the next decade. We support all greenhouse gases being included in the law, consistent with international climate frameworks.\nThe Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC) clearly states that methane reduction is critical to succeeding in tackling\n\nclimate change. Our climate law must include all greenhouse gases, including those from our biggest emitting sector - the\nagricultural sector. We support setting a gross emissions reduction target as well as a net emissions reduction target. We cannot rely\non planting trees alone to offset our emissions. We must seek to decarbonise our industry and transport systems. As the\n\nParliamentary Commissioner for the Environment stated in their submission to the Productivity Commission, June 2018, page 4: “Each\ntonne of emissions offset by forestry is a tonne not reduced at source. Relying too heavily on forestry could lead to continued high\n\nlevels of gross emissions. Pressure to reduce these after 2050 could entail a more costly and disruptive transition than a deeper\ntransition commenced earlier.” We support the ‘firewall’ principle that New Zealand’s targets must be achieved by actual reductions in\n\nour own domestic emissions and not through the purchase of overseas carbon credits or an over-reliance on forests as carbon\nsinks. We support setting legally binding climate budgets that are set at a bare-minimum ambition, which must be achieved or\nbettered by government within the prescribed timeframes. While budgets should be binding, policy recommendations from the\n\nCommission should be just that – recommendations. The world needs pathways to transformational change if we are to avoid\ncatastrophic warming. This is the scale of the challenge. The science is clear: the only way we can succeed is with big ambition. New\n\nZealand must be bold and pass strong law for the sake of our precious earth and future generations. We support the establishment\nof a Climate Change Commission. The commission’s role should include: • devising binding climate budgets • identifying the level of\n\nreduction for each form of greenhouse gas (long-lived and short-lived) • monitoring adherence to the set ‘firewall’ • monitoring\nprogress towards our targets • monitoring cumulative emissions • advising on adaptation. The Climate Change Commission should\n\nprovide advice to the New Zealand government. To ensure transparency and accountability, I support the Government being required\nto table all reports from the Climate Change Commission to Parliament. We support the Government preparing a National Climate Risk\nAssessment. The Government must be required to produce an Adaption Programme to address the climate risks identified in the\n\nNational Climate Risk Assessment. As authors of a guidebook on carbon farming (\"The Carbon Forest, 2010\") we observe that a weak\nETS has resulted in insignificant carbon emission reductions and a great sense of uncertainty. This uncertainty has prevented\n\nbusinesses from investing in (a) carbon sequestration, and (b) carbon emission reductions. The Zero Carbon Bill (and all government\nbehaviors) need to be coherent with our Paris Climate Agreement commitments in order to provide certainty for business decision\n\nmakers.\n\n\n\n You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
